Ms. Frieren.
（フェルン）フリーレン様
You're late.
（フリーレン）遅かったね
You defeated Aura, didn't you?
（フェルン）
アウラを倒したんですね
♪～
Like a fairy tale
It's a sign the story has reached its end
Like a single passage taken from
A journey that was too long
Of the evil that once cast a shadow
Across this land
And the memories of the short journey
With the hero who defeated it
Beyond Journey's End
The story ends
And the hero goes to sleep
Leaving this land with
Days of peace and quiet
The passage of time heartlessly
Makes people forget
Even the tracks left behind by his life
Begin to rust
Just the same
Your words and wishes and courage
Are still inside of me
And they live on
We chose the same path
That's all it was supposed to be
Why is it that at some point
I wanted to understand the reason for
The tears that fall down my cheeks
Even now
If I retrace the journey we walked together
Even though you're not there
I know I'll be able to find it
～♪
I don't believe—
I can't believe this happened.
（グラナト）信じられん
まさか こんなことが…
（フリーレン）行くよ
Let's go.
（グラナト）
待て　逃げる必要はない
Wait. You don't need to run.
（シュタルク）
伯爵は全部 不問にするってよ
The graf said he'd pardon you.
（グラナト）
激しい戦いであったろうに
It must have been a fierce battle,
but none of them are seriously damaged.
どれも大きな損傷はない
Thank you for treating the heroes
of the northern lands with respect.
感謝する
北側諸国の英傑たちに
よく敬意を払ってくれた
（フリーレン）前は もっと
派手にやっていたんだけどね
I used to cast flashier spells,
but Himmel got mad at me.
ヒンメルに怒られたから
（シュタルク）
そりゃ そうだろうな
I bet he did.
怒られて当然だ
He was right to be angry. I'd be angry, too.
Mr. Himmel trained you well.
（フェルン）ヒンメル様は
フリーレン様のしつけが上手ですね
（フリーレン）しつけって言うな
Don't say it like that.
でも まあ そうだよね
I guess you're right, though.
This is a normal reaction.
これが普通のリアクションだ
（フェルン）
どういうことですか？
What do you mean?
Don't worry about it.
（フリーレン）こっちの話
Fern, Stark.
フェルン
シュタルク
Good job defeating Lügner and his henchwoman.
よく リュグナーたちを倒した
I'm proud of you.
偉いぞ
（フェルン）フッ…
（シュタルク）ヘヘヘッ
I'd be even more impressed
if you weren't so beat up, though.
（フリーレン）
ボロボロじゃなければ
もっと よかったけど
（シュタルク）
このくらい 戦士なら普通だぜ
This is normal for a warrior.
（フェルン）普通って何だろう…
What does "normal" even mean?
（フリーレン）満身創痍(そうい)じゃん
You're covered in wounds.
See that they receive proper burials.
I'll escort our benefactors to the city.
丁重に弔ってやれ
彼女たちを街まで送る
Yes, milord.
（側近）はっ
（側近）閣下！
Milord.
What is it?
（グラナト）どうした
Frieren.
（グラナト）フリーレン
I've never been as grateful to anyone
as I am to you today.
わしは 今日ほど
誰かに感謝したことはない
Frieren, I promised to reward you
in any way I could.
（グラナト）フリーレン
確かに わしは
お前に できうるかぎりの
褒美を取らすと言った
You requested the defensive
barrier grimoire by Flamme
お前が望んだのは
防護結界について記された
グラナト家に代々伝わる⸺
that has been passed down
for generations in my family.
大魔法使い フランメの魔導書
Are you sure this is what you want?
This grimoire...
本当に こんな魔導書でいいのか？
この魔導書は…
（フリーレン）偽物
It's fake.
（グラナト）あ…
Yes. The defensive barrier it describes
そうだ
口伝により継承された
この街の防護結界魔法とは
is nothing like our city's barrier,
whose spell is passed down by oral tradition.
似ても似つかぬものだ
I'm well aware of that, milord.
（フリーレン）百も承知です 閣下
これは趣味ですので
It's just my hobby.
I see.
（グラナト）そうか
Either way, you needn't use
such formal language.
それより 堅苦しい言葉づかいは
なしにしよう
From your perspective,
I must seem akin to an infant.
お前から見れば わしなど
赤子のようなものだろう
I suffered a bitter experience when
I first left to defeat the Demon King.
（フリーレン）
魔王討伐の旅立ちの時
痛い目に遭ったもので
そういえば
ハイター様が言っていましたね
Come to think of it, Mr. Heiter
said that in the royal capital,
disrespecting nobility
is punishable by death.
王都では 貴族に対する非礼は
死罪だとか
ヒンメルとアイゼンが
王様に タメ口たたいて
Himmel and Eisen were nearly executed
for speaking casually to the king.
処刑されかけたんだよね
Remembering Himmel screaming
and crying takes me back.
懐かしいな
ヒンメルの泣き叫ぶ顔
（シュタルク）アハハハハ…
Execution? That's extreme.
死罪だなんて大げさな
And speaking so casually to me
is a serious crime in this town, brat.
それとな クソガキ
わしに タメ口たたくのは
この街では重罪だ
（シュタルク）悪いな おっさん
Sorry, old man.
この高そうな椅子 ぶっ壊すぜ
I'm gonna break this
expensive-looking chair.
ちゅ… 中央諸国は野蛮ですね
閣下 ハハハ…
Th-The central lands sure
are barbaric, milord.
マジかよ！
Seriously?!
（庭師）
裏庭の木 切り終えました
I've finished cutting the
trees in the backyard.
（グラナト）ご苦労
Thank you.
Well, you know, I only said that
so you'd escape.
まあ あれだ
あの時 言ったのは
小僧を逃がすための方便だ
In this town, you won't be thrown
in prison just for speaking casually.
タメ口程度で
牢(ろう)に放り込むような法は
この街にはない
Be at ease.
気にせず楽にしてくれ
In that case...
そういうことなら
よかったですね シュタルク様
Good news for you, Mr. Stark.
あっ…
He's passed out.
気絶してる
（ドアが開く音）
（グラナト）アウラ討伐の報は
街の者たちにも伝えておいた
I've told the townsfolk of Aura's defeat.
皆 英雄たちを
ねぎらいたがっている
They all want to honor the heroes.
I ask that you take your time here.
どうか ゆっくりしていってくれ
（子供）浮いてる
He's floating.
（シュタルク）
それほどでもないけど
It's not that big a deal.
The name that has protected me
Is being called by that soothing voice of yours
So that you won't close your eyes all alone
I'll embrace you
You joined your warm hands with mine
So I won't forget
Beyond the night, where it's full of flowers
It is where you are, a place I will return to
Split the swelling, unravel the darkness
So that the dream remains uncorrupted
To the blue path that never ends
（シュタルク）
買い出し 終わったぜ
I finished the shopping.
Shall we go, then?
（フェルン）では 行きましょうか
You're leaving already, Frieren?
（グラナト）もう旅立ちか？
フリーレン
Graf Granat.
（フリーレン）グラナト卿
（グラナト）門まで送ろう
I'll see you to the gates.
Frieren, I hear you're traveling to Ende,
（グラナト）フリーレン
お前は 魔王城のある⸺
大陸最北端のエンデを
目指しているそうだな
the farthest point north,
where the Demon King's castle is.
But currently, conditions on the
Northern Plateau aren't looking good.
だが 今は北部高原の情勢が
だいぶ悪いようでな
人の往来が制限されている
Travel is restricted.
冒険者の場合でも
Even adventurers must be accompanied
by a first-class mage.
一級魔法使いの同行が必要だそうだ
（フェルン）
なら フリーレン様がいるので
Then there should no problem
with Ms. Frieren by our side.
問題ありませんね
（フリーレン）
何？　その一級魔法使いって
What's a first-class mage?
（フェルン）フリーレン様
知らないんですか？
Ms. Frieren, you don't know?
大陸魔法協会が認定する
魔法使いの資格ですよ
It's a certification awarded by the
Continental Magic Association.
（フリーレン）資格？
Certification?
（フェルン）私も旅立ちの時
聖都で取得しました
I acquired mine in the
holy capital when we left.
ほら
See?
三級魔法使いの認定証
This is my third-class mage certificate.
（フリーレン）そういえば
何かやってたっけ…
Come to think of it, you did have
some business to take care of then.
今の資格って こんなんなんだ
Is this what certifications
look like these days?
（フェルン）フリーレン様
Ms. Frieren, don't tell me you're
an uncertified underground mage.
まさか 無資格の
闇魔法使いだったんですか？
（フリーレン）
闇医者みたいに言わないでよ
Don't make it sound like
I'm some back-alley doctor.
The organizations that regulate
mages are constantly changing.
だって魔法使いを管理する団体って
しょっちゅう変わるんだもん
いちいち 資格なんか
取ってらんないよ
I can't be bothered obtaining
a new certification every time.
I doubt this holy emblem works anymore.
どうせ この聖杖(せいじょう)の証しも
もう使えないんでしょ
What is that antique?
（フェルン）
何ですか？　その骨董(こっとう)品は
（シュタルク）さすがの俺でも
大陸魔法協会は知っている
Even I know about the
Continental Magic Association.
少なくとも
半世紀以上前から あるぜ
They've been around for over
half a century at the very least.
（フリーレン）全然 最近じゃん
That's barely anything.
It's a hassle when they change their
standards of conduct so frequently.
困るんだよね
頻繁に管理の基準を
変えられちゃうと
（フェルン）ともかく
このままでは先に進めません
In any case, we'll need to overcome
this problem before we continue.
I don't know the specifics,
あまり詳しくはないのですが
but I believe there's a place
in the northern lands
たしか 北側諸国でも
一級試験が
受けられる場所がありましたよね
where you can take the first-class exam.
The largest magical city in the
northern lands, Äußerst.
北側諸国最大の魔法都市
オイサーストだな
シュヴェア山脈を越えた
ずっと先だ
It's far beyond the Schwer Mountains.
You can follow the highway,
but it'll be a long journey.
街道沿いに進めばいいが
長い道のりになる
Frieren, the house of Granat will
never forget what you've done for us.
フリーレン
グラナト家は
この恩を決して忘れん
よい旅を
Safe travels.
あっ…
It's snowing.
雪だな
（フェルン）そろそろ冬ですね
It's almost winter.
（フリーレン）ここら辺の冬は
厳しいから 気をつけてね
The winters around here are bitter,
so be careful.
ナメていると死ぬよ
If you underestimate them, you'll die.
そんなに危ないんですか？
Is it really that dangerous?
知らないの？
Don't you know?
In the war against the Demon King's forces,
what do you think claimed the most lives?
魔王軍との戦いで
最も多くの人を殺したのは…
It was the winters of the northern lands.
北側諸国の冬だよ
（吹雪の音）
（フリーレン）ほらね 迷った
See? We're lost.
（倒れる音）
（フリーレン）どうしよう…
What are we going to do?
Episode 11: Winter in the Northern Lands
（フリーレン）迷った
We're lost.
28 years after the death of Himmel the Hero,
in the Decke region, located in the northern lands
I can't believe we got lost before
even entering the Schwer Mountains.
シュヴェア山脈に入る前に
遭難とか シャレにならないよ
Mr. Stark, wake up!
シュタルク様　起きてください
寝たら死にますよ
If you fall asleep, you'll die!
（シュタルク）うう…
Have jumbo-berry specials
always been this small?
ジャンボベリースペシャルって
こんなに小さかったっけ？
（フェルン）
知りませんよ そんなこと
Who cares about that right now?
What should we do?
どうしましょう
In these strong winds,
we can't transport him with magic.
この強風だと 魔法で飛ばして
運ぶわけにもいかないね
He'd probably be blown away.
たぶん どっかに飛んでっちゃう
Then we'll have to carry him.
（フェルン）
担いでいくしかないですね
He's heavy.
重い…
Why is he so heavy?
なんで この人
こんなに重いんですか？
（シュタルク）いいにおい…
You smell nice.
（フェルン）
置いていっていいですか？
Can I leave him behind?
（フリーレン）我慢して
Bear it for now.
There should be an emergency shelter
at the foot of the mountains.
麓まで行けば
避難小屋があるはず
Isn't that information
eighty years out of date?
（フェルン）
それ 80年前の知識ですよね？
Are we going to be all right?
大丈夫なんですか？
（フリーレン）よかった
Good.
まだ 定期的に
管理されているみたいだね
It's still being maintained regularly.
（クラフトの息遣い）
It seems like someone's inside.
何だか 人の気配がしますね
（クラフトの息遣い）
Perhaps someone arrived before us.
先客がいるのでしょうか？
We're going inside.
（フリーレン）とにかく入るよ
このままじゃ氷漬けになっちゃう
We'll freeze out here.
（クラフト）
ふんっ ふんっ ふんっ ふんっ！
いい いいぞ！　温まってきた！
Good! Very good!
I'm starting to feel warmer!
ふんっ ふんっ ふんっ ふんっ！
ふんっ ふん…
（フリーレン）お邪魔します
Excuse the intrusion.
Ms. Frieren, we can't stay here.
Let's look for someplace else.
（フェルン）フリーレン様
ここはダメでございます
他を探しましょう
え～ なんで？
What? Why?
（フェルン）
中に変態がいるからです
There's a pervert inside.
（ドアが開く音）
A pervert? That's awfully rude.
（クラフト）変態とは心外だな
（フェルン）
行きますよ　フリーレン様
Let's go, Ms. Frieren.
（クラフト）ん？　待て
Wait. Are you an elf?
お前 エルフか？
（フリーレン）ん？
It's been about 300 years since
I've met another of my kind.
（クラフト）同族と会うのは
300年ぶりくらいだな
I thought the elves had already died out.
エルフは もう
絶滅したのかと思っていたぞ
私もだよ
So did I.
嬢ちゃんも 火をありがとうな
And thanks for the fire, miss.
Not at all.
（フェルン）いえ…
I'm lucky I ran into a couple of mages.
魔法使いと会えたのは幸運だった
女神様の導きだな
The Goddess must have led you here.
シュヴェア山脈を
越えてきたんだが
I crossed the Schwer Mountains,
but this blizzard extinguished my coals.
この吹雪で
火種を失ってしまってな
凍える小屋の中 スクワットで
命をつないでいたんだ
I was keeping myself alive by doing
squats inside this freezing hut.
I see.
（フリーレン）なるほど
（フェルン）
よく分からないんですけど
I'm not sure I understand.
I'm Kraft the Monk.
モンクのクラフトだ
（フリーレン）
魔法使い フリーレン
Frieren the Mage.
Fern, also a mage.
（フェルン）
同じく魔法使いのフェルンです
こちらは 戦士のシュタルク様
This is Mr. Stark the Warrior.
（クラフト）しかし オレオール…
Anyway, Aureole, huh?
天国を目指す旅か
You're traveling to heaven, then?
信仰心が篤(あつ)いのはいいことだ
Good on you for being so pious.
半信半疑だけどね
I'm not sure I totally believe it.
（フェルン）フリーレン様
（フリーレン）ん？
Ms. Frieren.
Mr. Stark is getting colder.
So warm and comfortable...
（シュタルク）温かくて 心地いい
And that's one huge jumbo-berry special.
それに あんなに大きい
ジャンボベリースペシャル…
What happened to me?
俺… どうしちまったんだ？
We got caught in a blizzard, and then...
たしか 猛吹雪で…
ん？
あ…
誰 このおっさん！
Who is this guy?!
（驚く声）
You're so noisy.
（フリーレン）騒がしいなあ
（クラフト）せっかく 人肌で
温めてやったというのに
That's no way to thank someone
for warming you up with their body.
なんたる態度だ
（シュタルク）人肌って…
Their body?
あっ
おっさん いい体してんな
You've got a nice body, old man.
（フェルン）シュタルク様
Mr. Stark?
（シュタルク）
いや そういう意味じゃなくて…
No, not like that.
I mean he's got a nice body
from training hard.
よく鍛え上げられた いい体だ
You must be really strong.
あんた とんでもなく強いだろ
What's your name?
おっさん 名前は？
Kraft the Monk.
モンクのクラフト
I've never heard of you.
（シュタルク）聞いたことねえな
But you must be a pretty famous monk, right?
でも 名のあるモンクってのは
間違いねえだろ？
（クラフト）フッ…
Stark, rest here.
シュタルク
お前は ここで休んでいろ
２人は 食料を運ぶのを
手伝ってくれ
You two, help me bring in food supplies.
My wagon and cargo are nearby.
近くに 俺の荷車と積み荷がある
I'm really glad I met all of you.
本当に お前たちに会えてよかった
この凍った食料も
何とかなるだろう
We'll be able to use these frozen supplies.
遠慮せず使ってくれ
Use as much as you'd like.
You've certainly stocked up.
（フェルン）
量は十分にありますね
（フリーレン）このまま
シュヴェア山脈を越えるのは
Trying to cross the Schwer Mountains
in these conditions would be suicide.
自殺行為だし
ここで しばらくは足止めかな
We're stuck here for a while.
By the way, Frieren, do you know who I am?
（クラフト）ところで フリーレン
お前は 俺のことを知っているか？
Not at all.
（フリーレン）全然
I didn't think so.
（クラフト）だろうな
I don't know the first thing
about you, either.
俺も お前のことなんて
これっぽっちも知らん
She's the mage from the party of heroes.
勇者様御一行の魔法使いですよ
And before that?
（クラフト）その前は？
（フェルン）ん？
What do you mean?
何が言いたいの？
I mean that we're elves.
俺たちはエルフってことだ
It's been nearly six months.
（クラフト）
もうすぐ半年になるな
Thanks to all of you, we made it through
the long winter in the northern lands.
お前たちのおかげで 無事
北側諸国の長い冬を越えられた
Take this.
こいつを
フェルンに渡してやってくれ
Give it to Fern. She's a pious girl.
あの子は信仰心の篤い いい子だ
Must be because she was raised by a priest.
僧侶に育てられた影響だろうな
She never forgets to thank the Goddess.
女神様への感謝を忘れていない
クラフトは どうして
女神様を信じているの？
Kraft, why do you believe in the Goddess?
フリーレンは 信じていないんだな
You don't, do you?
Excluding during the age of mythology,
（フリーレン）天地創造の女神様は
神話の時代を除いて
the Goddess of Creation hasn't shown herself
once in the long history of this world.
この世界の長い歴史の中で
実際に姿を現したことは
一度もない
You're young. I used to think that way, too.
若いな
俺も 昔はそうだった
But now I believe in the Goddess
from the bottom of my heart.
だが今は 心の底から
女神様を信じている
いや…
No, I need her to exist.
いてくれなきゃ困るんだよ
Everyone who knew of my
righteous triumphs has died.
俺の成してきた偉業も正義も
知っているやつは皆 死に絶えた
So when I die, I'll go to heaven
and the Goddess will praise me.
だから俺は 死んだら 天国で
女神様に褒めてもらうんだ
She'll say, "Well done, Kraft."
“よく頑張った クラフト”
"You lived a fantastic life."
“お前の人生は
すばらしいものだった”ってな
You understand that, Frieren.
分かるだろ フリーレン
It's too cruel for the path your life took
to not be remembered by anyone.
自分の生きてきた軌跡が
誰にも
覚えられちゃいないってのは
あまりにも酷だ
We've lived a long time to get to this point.
俺たちは 長い人生を歩んで
ここにいるんだぜ
Kraft, that's just something we desire.
（フリーレン）クラフト
それは ただの私たちの願望だ
（クラフト）そうだな
You're right.
Does that apply to heaven too, Frieren?
天国もか？　フリーレン
No matter.
まあいい
お前の身の上を話せ
Tell me about yourself,
and I'll tell you about myself.
俺も話す
If you don't believe in the Goddess,
then I'll praise you instead.
お前が信じないっていうのなら
女神様の代わりに
俺が お前を褒めてやる
Are you surprised?
（ハイター）意外ですか？
（フリーレン）うん
Yeah. I didn't think you'd fund the
reconstruction of this village's orphanage.
まさか ハイターが
この村の孤児院の
復興資金を出すなんてね
（ハイター）ハハハハッ
You don't beat around the bush, do you?
正直ですね
I was an orphan, too.
私も孤児でしたから
きっと 女神様も
I'm sure the Goddess will praise me
for living a pure and proper life.
清く正しく生きた私を
褒めてくださることでしょう
What are you talking about, you corrupt
priest? You're drinking right now.
酒を飲みながら
何を言ってるんだ この生臭坊主は
Frieren.
（ハイター）フリーレン
（フリーレン）ん？
Do you have someone to praise you?
あなたには
褒めてくれる人はいますか？
Where did that come from?
急に どうしたのさ
You don't seem to believe in the Goddess,
あなたは 女神様を
信じていないようなので
so if you tell me about yourself,
I'll praise you instead.
身の上を話していただければ
代わりに私が褒めますよ
I haven't done much with my life.
（フリーレン）
だらだらと生きてきただけだよ
I haven't done anything praiseworthy.
褒められるようなことなんて
何もない
Even though you're constantly
suppressing your mana?
常に魔力を制限しているのに？
（フリーレン）ん…
To me, that seems like the
result of tremendous effort.
それは 血のにじむような
努力の賜物(たまもの)に見えますが
Something that would take
a lifetime to accomplish.
それこそ 人生を懸けたような
You noticed?
（フリーレン）
気がついていたの？
（ハイター）何年 一緒に
旅をしていると思っているんですか
How many years have we
traveled together again?
It's not an interesting story.
（フリーレン）面白い話じゃないよ
I don't mind.
（ハイター）かまいませんよ
それに後学のためにもなります
Besides, it sounds like something
useful to know for the future.
（フリーレン）なんで？
Why?
Perhaps a child of mine will become a mage.
もしかしたら 私の子供は
魔法使いになるかもしれませんよ
（フリーレン）
僧侶は生涯 独身でしょ
I thought priests couldn't marry.
（ハイター）ハハハハッ…
（フリーレン）フッ
Why do so many strange
people serve the Goddess?
なんで 女神様に仕える連中は
変なやつが多いんだろうね
I'll pass. I've already had
someone else praise me.
遠慮しておくよ
もう別のやつに
褒めてもらったから
そうか
I see. You have good friends, Frieren.
いい友人を持ったな フリーレン
大事にしろ
You should cherish them.
Actually, he's already...
いや その人は もう…
He's in heaven now.
今は天国にいるよ
Then you'll see him again someday.
（クラフト）なら いずれ会えるな
You're right.
（フリーレン）そうだね
I'm going this way.
（クラフト）俺は こっちだ
フリーレン
今生の別れとは思わん
Frieren, I doubt this is
the last time we'll meet.
何百年後かに またな
I'll see you in a few centuries.
Take care, old man! I had fun!
おっさんも元気でな！
楽しかったぜ
（フェルン）ペンダント
ありがとうございました！
Thank you for the pendant!
♪～
And you alright
Can you hear me
Trailing along deserted train tracks
Crying excessively
Wanting you to smile
I hold on to memories I'd like to keep fresh
There's something I'd like to tell you
With words more precious than a goodbye
Unremarkable yet special
See, things that couldn't have been
Seen if it weren't for these eyes
Why? They begin to overflow
So, if I were to be born again
I would surely choose this place once more
So, if we were to meet again
I'd never let you go, I'd choose the present
Even if no promises were made
Even if I'm lost in days of loneliness
Those tears will be alright,
dawn will surely break
I'm whispering our lullaby
～♪
for you to come back home
His pure white cape proves that he's
I'm a mild-mannered person,
but even I'm pissed off.
This village used to protect the Hero's Sword.
the strongest warrior in the village.
It's a replica.
They're a gift to honor warriors
who have worked hard.
Perv.
We're not warriors.
Don't tell the rest of the family.
Episode 12
A Real Hero
He was a real hero.